I don't know if I believe in God or not.  I have
believed in God,
that is an undeniable thing,
but, after seeing the world,
how it works,
science, how it works, I
doubt it, I doubt it, the truth.
I believe in science, in what I see,
in what I can demonstrate empirically, in people.  I
believe in ourselves, I
believe that we do not depend on any
force majeure, or any destiny, or anything.
I believe in you, I believe in me, I
believe in us.  Where do we
come from?  Where are we going?  Who are we?
Are we an accident of nature
or children of an almighty god?
And when we die, are we reincarnated,
is it a black hole
or do we meet our creator?  Are
we soul, are we matter,
or just the fruit of the imagination?
Are we the only species in the galaxy,
or are they hiding from us that we are not alone?
What do we know
and what do we believe?
Does everything happen by magic,
or is there always an explanation?
And magic is magic until science learns to see the trick.
And, if you want to find these tricks,
you have no choice but to look for...
"The Other Side".  Let's
see, it can't be that difficult.
Who needs recipes
when you have self-confidence?  I
only have four eggs, but I'm fully confident that they'll be enough.  I
don't have a blender, but I think
the Minipimer will do the trick.
Ugh... I don't see it clearly, huh?  I don't
know, I, yes...
What the hell, yes I can.  You
just need to project positivity
and trust the universe.  I take a
deep breath,
I let go of bad energies
and I fill myself with light.
What a shitty cake!
Maybe I didn't have enough faith
in myself.
Oh my God, it's disgusting!
Oh my, oh my, I'm late!
Rocío, how are you?  Man
!  A pleasure.
Enchanted, here.
Welcome to the Science Museum.
Paradise.  It
is a wonderful place.
A paradise, for you.
And today I would like to talk
about different things:
science, obviously;
where are the limits of science;
about pseudoscience,
which you have a lot to say about,
and about the beliefs
that people have.
Enchanted.
It's the theme of my channel,
so I'm in my element.
Perfect.  Well, come on, let's go.
Let's be there.
What's coming today
is pretty juicy,
so please
stay tuned.
Rocío Vidal is a journalist, science popularizer...
and Schrödinger's Cat on YouTube.
In February 2018, he opened a science and critical thinking channel
to arouse the curiosity
of young people and make them think.
And, currently, it
exceeds 450,000 subscribers.
With a
sarcastic and humorous informative tone,
Rocío sifts through the sieve
of science influencers,
large companies,
beliefs and renowned philosophers,
but also has arrepleguists,
ufologists
and all kinds of pseudoscience.
Hold on tight, this woman
has no hair on her tongue,
but she does have a lot of science in her pocket.  When
you were little,
were you one of those girls... who
asked questions all day and wondered why everything was happening?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
Yes, it was a bit heavy, I think.
It's true that I didn't handle the issue of why yes, why no very well.
I wanted explanations of things.
And then,
you decided to do Journalism,
perhaps because, since you asked yourself so many questions,
it was like the profession
that asks questions.
Yes, exactly.
And, in part, it was the issue of information, right?, objectivity...
And then, of course, you
get to Journalism and say:
"No objectivity, nothing, right?
Everyone is super biased
and we have our prejudices,
objectivity doesn't exist
and all that."
And you're like, "Now what?
Now what do I do with my life?"
And now about two years ago you decided to open a YouTube channel
and talk, of course, about science.
Why?  What were you looking for?
I think that, when I finished my
degree and specialized, I
wanted to balance, right?,
the battle,
the lack of scientific culture...
I wanted to add my own twist to all of this
and said:
"Well, why not, right?
If now, with very few resources,
a cell phone and being at home,
you can open a channel
and see what's happening, right?"
And the name, Schrödinger's Cat, where does it come from?
To be honest... I
could give you a super-profound explanation but it would be a lie
and then the truth, what do you want?
The short one.
The short one?  The short story is the truth.
Perfect.
The short story is that I liked
quantum physics,
hence Schrödinger's Cat.  I
wanted to give it a feminine touch, that's why the cat, right?
She's a woman spreading science,
and because I like cats.  I
mean... It had everything, it
was perfect, the name.
There's a video of yours,
which would be the boom...
and from which everyone
knows Schrödinger's Cat,
which is "Modern Shamans".
And I have it here on my iPad
and I'd like you to look at it.  Let's
remember that.  Let's
see what you remember.
This is the most complicated video I've
made because of what it involves.
But there are few things
that bother me more in this world
than people who take advantage of vulnerable people
to sable them with empty promises and shamanic magic,
and more,
without having any idea about it.
"What is the case
with these two girls."
About 8 months ago, he
changed the style of his channel and became more mystical, more alternative.
And what better presentation video than her
talking about the 100% effectiveness of
the law of attraction.
(woman) "Everything in the universe
is energy."
"Our emotions,
ourselves,
even our thoughts."
"These energies attract everything
we focus on."
"We all learn in school
that energy is
neither created nor destroyed, it
transforms, it transforms
into whatever you choose."
Why did you make this video?
How young, huh? I was.
How happy, with a thousand subscribers...
But that was two years ago.
Well, I look very young. You
still do.
Well, thank you.
No, but yes, the pressure of not having so many subscribers and all that...
Why did I make the video?
Because I think I saw
that they were very influential girls
and I thought: "Wow, it's a scam."
And I said: "Well, totally,
no one will watch the video.
I have a thousand subscribers,
my mother will see it..."
And everyone saw it.
Everyone saw it. Was there any
repercussions? Did you
get messages, did
someone say something to you?
Since that video, the "hater" was like something that was always there.
But, well, I don't want to think,
if "hate" came to me,
how much "hate" would
come to them, right?
It's also something
that made me feel bad...
thinking that in the end
social networks are like that,
that you take one thing
and everything catches fire.
Speeches like the ones they make, do you think they are dangerous?
Yes, I think so.
These girls
came as an aura cleansing,
chakra cleansing
and all these things, they
sold stones
to cure you things...
Really, with a speech
that is pseudoscientific, right?,
and that is dangerous because of what they do, right?,
because they are posing as doctors when they are not.
Mm...
A pseudoscience
would say that it is a...
science that is not  empirical at all.
When we talk about pseudoscience we are talking about a discipline or theory
that presents itself as scientific, but it is not.
No, I do not think that magic stones give you any power,
but perhaps they do suggest that you
do things of a different type
that you would not do if you did not have them.
That, I am very sorry,
that is not science.
Science
must be based on a few steps, on
a hypothesis that you make,
on an experiment,
and see that your results
are correct.
Pseudoscience does not do this;
therefore, it is bad science.
(woman) What is, for me, science?
It is a way that humans have of finding answers
to the questions that we have about the world
and the universe in general. We
would not be doing this program, without science, perhaps.
Well, certainly not.
You have been to conferences, right?,
where there are flat-earth experts,
people who talk about
extraterrestrial life...
We have made a summary of them, in this video. Surely you remember those moments.
Sure. I
wanted to ask you your  impressions of this event...
Sure, man, Enrique de Vicente.
...that we have been visited
by UFOs.  meow
"Greetings to the cat."
"Hello."
"From Schrödinger."
I know pilots who have taken filming, military pilots.
They are ships that descend,
that come from another world.  They
don't behave like our ships.
Do we have the legitimate right
to doubt science,
or is science sacrosanct?
Let's consider that.
Do we know that the Earth is spherical
or do we believe that it is spherical?
None of us
has gone into space.
What a moment...
Man.
A surreal point?
I was freaking out.
...electromagnetic
with two rods.
So, sometimes they cross,
sometimes they separate.
If they separate, there is positive
or good energy;  if they get together, why not.
Mm...
If he's intelligent, he doesn't control his
emotions, then it's a disaster.
"You don't like being where you are,
nor who you are with, because you fall."
Then we will see why it falls.  Emotional intelligence.
Breathe, let the good come in, let
the bad come out...
Go [ __ ] yourself, I'm getting in, huh?
Two types of reality: objective reality is this table...
But I do it like that on camera
and it doesn't show. OK?
That's the objective reality.
But subjective reality is... Ah!
Ah!
You feel something, I did
n't want to do too much... I did
n't feel anything. I'm
Schrödinger's Cat, it's difficult.
Sure. Is there
anything
that really impacted you,
like, "They left me
out of the game here"?
At the Ufology Congress, there were like many types of people,
there were like expert ufologists who showed you evidence and everything,
and you thought: "Maybe, man, maybe there are aliens and they're out there."
But later, at the same congress,
there was another guy
who told me that he had inside him
the Martian Arthurian Julian,
from I don't know what planet. And I
, of course, was like... everything has
already gone to [ __ ],  you know? It does
n't make sense.
And in all this show, let's say,
when you go to these conferences
and talk to these people,
have you learned anything?
There's one thing I do admire.
In fact, the flat-earther who spoke says something that is true,
and that is that many people know things,
but they don't know why.
The Earth is spherical?
Yes, we all know that.
But how many people could explain
why the Earth is spherical?
And it's something to admire, isn't it?
I always think that you have to have an open mind, Carl Sagan said, you have to
have an open mind,
but don't let your brain fall, right?, on the ground.
In other words, you have to find a balance.
People who question things so much
, that's good,
because it's curiosity, it
's critical thinking.
Of course, if you then get to the extreme of thinking that the Earth is flat,
it's like: "'So much mess'
to get here?"
Because it's not flat, really, right, the  Earth? It's not, surely, 100%?
What do you see here? They're deceiving us, NASA is deceiving us. It's
not flat, but it's "hollow".
The Earth is round. Totally.
The problem of whether the Earth
is flat or round... I
think it depends on the point of view.
A person who dedicates himself
to traveling around the Mediterranean
perfectly for him
the Earth is flat.
A person who dedicates himself
to pulling GPS
needs to think
that the Earth is round.
I believe that the Earth is round
because there are astronauts out there,
in satellites,
who see the Earth
and the Earth is round. They
say that there is no cliff
to fall off. I
can tell you directly that the Earth is round and you would be happy,
but I think that, really,
there is an important philosophical issue
of science behind it.
Ugh, it's because Galileo died because of that. The Earth is round. No, no, no.
Because, precisely, that's how science has evolved, many times:
questioning things
that were considered well-founded
and giving way to new ideas. We'll
be in good company here,
from what I see.
We're in very good company.
We're not that different, eh? It
's been a long time, but...
Yeah.
Man, physically, a little, aren't we?
Look, who is this?
This is Lucy. She
's the first Australopithecus ever
found.
And, look at her,
even though she's small, oh my...
See how we're not that different?
She must have had the same problems as us.
Look, the same toes...
A little more hair, that's for sure.
Well, than you, I don't know, than me, yes.
Lucy came out hairy for us.
Yes, yes, a little, a little.
Rocío, the ones I don't see anywhere
are Adam and Eve.
No. No, they're not there. Well, Lucy, I
think she's our Eve, isn't she?
Is she our Eve?
The Eve of science.
Well, look...
Let's leave her there.
Adam... we'll find him.
Yes, it doesn't matter that much.
These two, a  He's dead,
quite dead.
The other one is still looking at him.
Hm-hm.
And what I see is that performances were already being made, at this time, eh?,
with the theme of burial
and such...
Performance is part
of our life, yes, yes.
Look, here we see how the rituals,
the symbolism, the allegories...
All this, all the beliefs already...,
the fear of death, was already very present since the beginning of time.
Neanderthals were
already looking at the stars
and already thinking: "What's up here?"
They were asking themselves things:
"Who are we?  Where are we going?
What is the meaning
of our life?"
Before, they looked at the stars
and saw gods.
Now we know
that the stars exist,
that there is no God and that...
there are things that we already know, right?
It's like we've relegated
religion to a "back seat".
Deep down, people will always try to find an explanation...
about life or about our world.
So, the easy solution...
is to think that there is
a great creator.
I'm a practicing person,
I go to mass every day,
and I don't find
that there is any contradiction
between being a practicing Catholic,
in my case, and being a scientist.
What happens is, when you talk
to a believer,
you tell them: "Yes, the big bang
is the beginning of the universe",
but that person will always tell you:
"But who made the big bang?"
And that's how they will always try to find
the beginning of everything.
Science tries to answer questions about empirical facts,
about the things that surround us.
And religions
answer questions from each person,
of their faith and the hope they
have.
For me, the problem
is that, historically,
faith and religion have always been trampling on scientific knowledge,
or blocking it, right? Do
you believe in God, or not?
No.
Zero?
I have doubts,
I am an atheist "de facto",
which is because I am not sure that God does not exist,
but, I, I am living my life as if he did not exist, you know?
Our grandparents, probably,
most of our grandparents,
were very religious people, that generation.
And, now, our generation
believes less and less in God.
But we still need to believe
in something, I suppose.
What do we believe in?
In other things, right?
But I think that, among young people,
Catholic or Christian morality
has already become a bit of a thing, right?
But everyone needs to believe, or almost everyone,
and that is why more alternative spiritualities come out
, "new age",
beliefs in energies,
beliefs in the universe...
They are  other things,
which are not exactly the same,
but also because they fill
a void, right?, that there is.
Of course, therefore,
we have evolved a lot, haven't we?
Because... compared to him,
we keep doing these shows, eh?
Yes, yes, yes.
And we ask ourselves the same questions,
or almost the same ones, don't we?
Obviously, we have many more answers thanks to science,
not thanks to religion,
that's the question, right?
Thanks to science, we have advanced
and we know much more about our universe,
but still... there is so
much to do, so much to do...
In that problem
of not knowing,
belief has always helped us
to have as a basis
on which not to feel
that we are falling into a void. It
is difficult to have certainties,
in life. It is very difficult.
And, in fact, of certainties there are
the empirical ones of science;
the rest, everything that can be subjective, must be questioned.
That no one is
ever completely wrong,
nor is anyone
ever completely in what is true.
The fact that there are fewer and fewer people who believe, I think  which is due to the fact
that science has increasingly
answered more... more questions, right?
The fact
that each time science demonstrates
that there are things that are not directly created by God, that
God did not create man as such, but that there is an evolution,
makes people question
whether the faith and belief they
had in this religion
is good or not. They
may even feel deceived, because something...
that they have always been told that it is always
like this and that there is no doubt,
is questioned and empirically proven not to be so.
We were talking, weren't we?,
about the need to believe,
but why does it then
become so difficult... to
stop believing some things? It
's because we are slaves to our opinions and our beliefs.
And social networks don't help either, is that true?
Because with all the "jungle" that is being on Twitter, for example,
how are you going to change your mind
about something? They eat you up
.
And we have all the biases and everything  This,
all our prejudices
from the beginning,
which already make it very difficult for us to
change our minds. I've
heard you talk
about confirmation bias many times,
and now you've said the key word: "bias".
What would it be, confirmation bias?
It's the king of the crown,
what makes us feed so much on what we like, what we already know,
which is very difficult, because we already reject everything that comes to us that's new.
And this...
social networks take advantage of it,
politics take advantage of it,
to polarize, to debate,
for other things,
and it's very difficult for us to
change our minds,
because our brain feeds on what it already knows and likes.
Maybe that's why it's so difficult for us to be self-critical, sometimes to
say: "Sorry, that wasn't like that." It
costs a lot, too.
That's also a bit of pride, to say: "I was wrong." It
freaks me out, to be wrong,
for someone to tell me:  "That's not how it is." Are we
all, more or less, biased?
Yes, yes, yes, everyone, everyone.
What a scandal.
What you can do is fight with
your own prejudices, but... it
's impossible to fight completely.
And we have to be aware of it
and go through life
with a certain humility of thinking:
"Maybe I'm wrong."
Because, of course, Rocío, I
don't know if we have very thin skin...
and when someone questions
our beliefs we
jump up and get angry,
because of what you say.
Of course, it's normal, these are things that are part of our identity.
A flat-earther, a believer...
You, if you directly attack
their source, their essence,
how can they not get angry?
It's normal, right? We all get angry...
when things
that are important to us affect us. That's
why it's so difficult to
change our minds,
because we make our opinions a very
important part
of our lives.
Yes, a little.
Yes, it's hard for me, to do  self-criticism.
I think it's hard for people to
change their minds, sometimes,
when, like me, they're stubborn,
but they're stubborn in their own way.
I believe that
because I believe that's how it is and because I have an opinion above everyone else.
If I give you only
strawberry ice cream,
obviously, you'll only have eaten that, you won't have tasted anything else.
But there's a world of ice cream
in life that you also have to see, right?
Getting people to change their way of seeing the world is very difficult
and the reason why
is also difficult to explain.
I like strawberry, I
like vanilla better. I
think it's about trying, it
's about looking at yourself in a mirror...
and everything you've believed up until now
is not real.
And that's about breaking
all your patterns. I
think it's hard to be self-critical and give way to the opinions of others
because many times these opinions imply a change in life.
So,
if you consider something...
that you see that dismantles, a little,
the  schemes...
or it takes you
out of your comfort zone, you
probably won't want to leave that comfort zone
and you won't change your mind.
The brain, by itself, has a lot of trouble saying no or contradicting things.
So, as soon as a person...
who has ideas that are quite
established in themselves is
told no or that they have to
change them, it has a lot of trouble.
I think that, in general, people don't have a hard time changing their minds...
if they sell it to us
through, for example, television news...
or channels that reach us directly and that we believe. Whether
you like it or not,
changing something that you've thought about since you were a child
is very difficult. That's what
happened to me.
I grew up
in a Muslim family
and, whether you like it or not, always, if I'm in danger, I always turn to religion,
even if I don't want to,
in the end I do it.
I think it's more mental
than anything else. I do
n't know if you've noticed,
maybe not, because we were talking,
but we're dealing with a  big brain.
How long has it been since you went
inside a brain?
The other day I went
inside a brain. It's warm. Do you
mind going back in?
Yes, come on. Yes, yes, it's cool.
Oh, how cool!
Well, I didn't imagine it like that, me.
No, eh? It
's true that it's not bad inside a brain.
I told you it was warm.
I, on the other hand, thought it would be
a cold place, the brain.
Why?
Because it's so high up...
And because it's the rational part, right?
The rational part is cold, the heart is... It's
hot.
And I was noticing that,
that they give the feeling that they're
like wires, that they're neurons,
but, does the comparison that
humans are maybe like robots...
and that we're programmed
by beliefs help?
Ugh... Let's see...
I want to think that no, that we're not robots, that we have room for change,
I think it's possible,
but they make it difficult for us, eh?
It's just that sometimes  we are like a lot...
Yes, we are very obsessed, yes.
Not only social networks,
but also big companies...
It's that they want us to
continue with our beliefs,
because, the more we like being
on a social network,
the more information
we like,
all this more time we are going
to spend on social networks,
and that's rubbish.
They know that we are radicalizing, polarizing,
all thanks to their networks, but they do nothing, because it doesn't suit them.
So, do you think that this way of being of humans... is
leading us to be
a super-polarized society?
Yes, more and more. It
's discouraging,
but I think that we have to do an exercise, also, ourselves,
and exercise critical thinking,
be more aware...
that everyone
has their own personality,
their own experiences, their own beliefs, and respect that, right? I
don't know, balance.
So, it goes through a personal exercise, having to break dogmas,
and the question is:
which ones do you have,  to break up?
Ugh...
I think it's possible that you like reggaeton and be a good person.
It's a joke.
Yes, I know, I do. Do you
like reggaeton?
No. But, well, if you ask me,
I'll start listening to it.
I don't know,
maybe I like it and I don't know.
No, I like that
you're so curious. And
there's that phrase.
You have to watch out
because "curiosity killed the cat".
Tomorrow I'm "hanging out"
at the disco. I
want to see it. I
want to see it, that.
By the way, look... I'm
a little embarrassed to
tell you this,
but I'm reading a book,
"The Secret"...
Ugh, that thing about the law of attraction, right?,
that the universe conspires "in your favor".
Exactly, that the universe does
n't understand no, you
can't say "I don't want to be poor" because the universe will make you poor;
you have to say "I want to be rich".
What a bastard, the universe, huh?
The universe is... a bastard.
So, I don't know
if believing in something a lot...
makes it come true, in the end. I'm sorry to
say it, but no, huh?
No?
Me, more than believing in the law
of attraction, I'm sorry,
but I would put in the effort, I would put in the "effort" and I would put in the desire,
that's what's important.
And you'll achieve everything, for sure.
In the end, in this life,
everything works by trial and error.
Come on, 30 minutes at 180 degrees...
and hope that this time I've
done everything right.
-Holy crap!
-(man) Is it gone?
This time I followed the method.
I guess having faith that things will turn out well isn't enough.
Finally!
Now I understand why they say that patience is the mother of science.